Guide to the David Peck Todd Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
David Peck Todd papers
1862-1939
MS 496B
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
46.25
(125 boxes, 1 folio)
Correspondence, writings, records of astronomical expeditions, diaries, notebooks and scrapbooks of David Peck Todd, astronomer and teacher at Amherst College from 1881 to 1917. Between 1882 and 1914 Todd conducted nine expeditions to various parts of the world to study solar eclipses. The notes, photographs, drawings and memorabilia of these expeditions make up a significant portion of the papers. He was also a fertile inventor, and plans and drawings for many devices, some related to solving technical problems encountered on his expeditions are included in the papers.
Todd, David P. (David Peck), 1855-1939
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Millicent Todd Bingham, in 1970.
Existence and Location of Copies
Newspaper and magazine articles on astronomical subjects and Amherst College are available on microfilm (1 reel, 35mm.) from Manuscripts and Archives, Yale University Library, at cost. Order no. HM67.
Related Material
Loomis-Wilder Family Papers, MS 469A; Mabel Loomis Todd Papers, MS 496C; Millicent Todd Bingham Papers, MS 496D; Todd-Bingham Picture Collection, MS 496E; Todd-Bingham Memorabilia Collection, MS 496F.
Arrangement
Arranged in six series: I. Correspondence, Pre-1922. II. Scientific Subjects and Expeditions. III. Writings. IV. Teaching and Lecturing. V. Post-1922 Correspondence and Papers. VI. Personal and Financial.
Separated Materials
Photographs and glass plates were been incorporated in the Todd-Bingham Picture Collection, Ms. Group No. 496E.
Scope and Contents
One of the major characteristics of the David Peck Todd Papers is the extensive collection of printed matter, newspaper clippings and memorabilia that accompany the more conventional core of the collection: i.e., the correspondence and manuscript material. The papers have, accordingly, been organized into seven series that reflect the nature and variety of this material. Detailed notes on the contents and arrangement of each series are at the beginning of each section of the register in which is listed the contents of that series.
Biographical / Historical
David Peck Todd was born on March 19, 1855, in Lake Ridge, New York, the third child of Sereno Edwards and Rhoda Peck Todd. Through his father's line, he was descended from Jonathan Edwards, although, unlike their famous ancestor, his own father and grandfather were farmers. Sereno Edwards Todd was interested in scientific agriculture, and in addition to farming he wrote steadily for popular magazines and newspapers. He also published three books: The Young Farmer's Manual, The Apple-Culturist, and Todd's Country Houses. The uncle, on his mother's side, for whom David Peck Todd was named was a minister in Sunderland, Massachusetts.
When David Todd was still a child, the family moved to Brooklyn where he began his education. In 1870 he entered Columbia College, but after two years, at the urging of his uncle, he transferred to Amherst College, which was a few miles from Sunderland. He took his B.A. degree at Amherst in 1875. By this time his early work on astronomy, including an article on Jupiter's satellites published in the Astronomische Nachrichten in 1875, had attracted the attention of Simon Newcomb, head of the U.S. Naval Observatory in Washington. When Newcomb offered Todd a temporary post as an assistant at the Observatory, he accepted it, and went to Washington in August 1875 to begin work. In 1878, Newcomb moved to the American Ephemeris and Nautical Almanac and Todd followed him to that office as his chief computing and printing assistant. In his new post he met Eben Jenks Loomis, whose daughter, Mabel, he married on 5 March 1879.
In 1881, President Seelye of Amherst College invited Todd to return to the college as an instructor in astronomy and as Director of the Observatory. Todd accepted and brought his wife and their year-old daughter, Millicent, to Amherst for an eventful stay of nearly forty years. After living for a few years in rented houses, they finally built their own house, "The Dell," in 1888. (The specifications for this house are in Series VI.) The young couple rapidly became important, if controversial, members of the community, with Mabel Todd's involvement with the Dickinson family providing the family both with enduring fame and temporary notoriety. In 1890, Mabel Todd, in collaboration with Colonel Thomas Wentworth Higginson, brought out the first published volume of Emily Dickinson's poems. She had transcribed and arranged these over a period of years from the scraps entrusted to her by Emily Dickinson's sister, Lavinia. Significant as this event was in literary history, it was overshadowed in Amherst by Mabel Todd's affair with Emily Dickinson's brother, William Austin Dickinson, an affair which ran its curious course almost from their first meeting until Austin's death in 1895.
During his years at Amherst, David Todd erected one permanent monument to his stay there—the New Observatory. Although he had originally been told on his accepting the Amherst appointment that funds had been promised for a new observatory, the expected donor did not, in fact, leave Amherst the bequest it had expected. Todd, therefore, set about raising the money himself and in 1905 had the satisfaction of seeing the Observatory opened, as well as "Observatory House," a residence for himself and his family built nearby.
His major astronomical interest was in eclipses of the sun, and in pursuit of the best viewing spots for these phenomena he mounted nine expeditions between 1882 and 1914, some to distant parts of the world. (For reports, photographs, memorabilia, see Series II.) To solve the problem of getting many photographs of the eclipse in rapid succession during the brief period of totality, he devised a system of cameras operated by a foot pedal and perforated tape that made possible several hundred pictures during the few critical minutes. This apparatus was first used on his expedition to Japan in 1896, but conditions were so cloudy that the device did not get its real test until the eclipse of 1905 in Tripoli.
On all but two of these expeditions he was accompanied by his wife, who may have been responsible for helping to accumulate the great number of photographs that are part of this collection. In addition to the scientific photographs, the Todds brought back "picturesque" photographs of local people, views of scenery, street scenes, and buildings wherever they went. From the perspective of 19th century United States, North Africa, the East Indies, Peru and Japan were little known and rarely visited, and both Todds took advantage of their opportunities to see and record what they could of those places. On their return to the United States, both lectured professionally on their travel experiences which, from a popular point of view, loomed even larger than their scientific findings.
Unfortunately, Todd was dogged by ill-luck on his expeditions, four of which were ruined by heavy clouds at the moment of eclipse. A fifth, the expedition to Pernambuco, Brazil, in 1919, was a total loss because the ship carrying the party broke down and was delayed so long that the expedition did not get to its site until one month after the eclipse. For all the expeditions, however, there was one constant—the problem of transporting and installing sophisticated and delicate equipment in primitive sites, under unforeseeable conditions. This called for a kind of mechanical ingenuity that Todd delighted in displaying, e.g., improvising apparatus for moving heavy telescopes, building encampments, and recruiting and integrating local labor with his imported team of specialists. While many problems had to be solved on the spot, others raised questions that Todd tried to solve at leisure. His designs for a compressed air tank for use at high altitudes, for example, grew out of his own experience with altitude sickness in Japan and Peru. The possibilities of new kinds of telescopes and mountings continually interested him, and he published his proposals in a number of learned journals. In considering ways of overcoming the atmospheric disturbances that had ruined so many of his expeditions, Todd began to think of photography from the air, which had the double advantage both of being above the clouds, and also of extending the period of time available for observation. Todd's experiments in this field began in 1910 with a series of balloon ascents, and went on with attempts in later years to use the airplane to carry photographic equipment.
These immediate interests represented only a part of his abiding fascination with technology, industrial development, and anything that might come under the rubric of "progress." Although many of his inventions never got past the planning stage, his notes and drawings reveal a broad range of interests outside his profession. He worked on more or less detailed schemes for dredging machines, track-laying devices, electric organs, schemes for high-speed urban transport, and even a program for eternal life called "Vital Engineering." Indeed, he continued to devise new mechanical ideas and new schemes—designs for cities, world government, peace plans—until the last years of his life.
During his years at Amherst, Todd was a popular teacher, well-known for his easygoing, humorous style and his frequent compassionate interventions on the part of students in difficulties. He was often called upon by alumni groups to address them at reunion dinners where he was known as an entertaining speaker. He was also a voluminous writer and published three popular handbooks on astronomy. His New Astronomy for Beginners, which first appeared in 1897, went through twenty-five editions and was translated into Japanese and Hungarian. In addition to his articles in scientific journals, he also wrote frequently on astronomy for the popular press and contributed science notes regularly to the Nation between 1881 and 1915.
By 1917, however, signs of oncoming mental illness had grown too serious to ignore, and the Board of Trustees of Amherst College decided to retire him at full pay rather than let him serve out his term of tenure to 1920. In 1922, his erratic and excitable behaviour had become so serious that his family arranged to have him hospitalized. Except for brief periods, he remained in one or another nursing home or hospital until his death on June 1, 1939.
In this last period of his life, he continued to carry on correspondence with friends, family and publishers; he wrote interminable notes, poems, and observations on politics, interested himself in various land-development schemes, and continued to draw designs for new machines. He also continued his astronomical interests, and for the 1925 eclipse in New York, arranged to have an Army plane make photographs under his direction. These photographs were successful and copies are in the collection. As late as 1932, he went to Maine with his daughter and a party of friends for a rather playful observation of the eclipse of August 31 of that year.
His personal papers, memorabilia, and correspondence are at Yale University Library (Manuscripts and Archives), together with the papers of his wife, Mabel Loomis Todd, and of their daughter, Millicent Todd Bingham.
For a chart outlining the genealogical relations of the David Peck Todd, please consult the Genealogical Chart.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
American Journal of Science; Aeronautics; Astronomy; Balloons; Courtship; Eclipses; Education; Inventions; Mars (Planet) -- Opposition, 1907; Observatories; Science; Venus (Planet) -- Transit -- 1874; Women authors; Women; Africa; Amherst (Mass.); Angola; Asia; Chile; Esashi-shi (Japan); Europe; Latin America; Middle East; Panama; Peru; Saint Helena; Shirakawa-shi (Japan); Singkep (Indonesia); Soviet Union -- Description and travel; Tripoli (Libya); West Indies; Diaries; Astronomers; Educators; Abbe, Cleveland, 1872-1934; Agassiz, Alexander, 1835-1910; Allen, Francis Richmond, 1843-1931; Babbott, Frank Lusk, 1854-1933; Bailey, Alice Ward, 1857-1922; Baker, Ray Stannard, 1870-1946; Barnard, Edward Emerson, 1857-1923; Bingham, Millicent Todd, 1880-1968; Bridgman, Herbert L. (Herbert Lawrence), 1844-1924; Bryce, James Bryce, Viscount, 1838-1922; Cable, George Washington, 1844-1925; Cannon, Annie Jump, 1863-1941; Derr, Louis, 1868-1923; Dickinson, Lavinia Norcross, 1833-1899; Dickinson, Austin, 1829-1895; Elkin, William L. (William Lewis), 1855-1933; Flammarion, Camille, 1842-1925; Frost, Edwin Brant, 1866-1935; Grubb, Howard, Sir, 1844-1931; Hall, Asaph, III, 1829-1907; Hall, G. Stanley (Granville Stanley), 1844-1924; Harris, George, 1844-1922; Hartness, James, 1861-1934; Headley, P. C. (Phineas Camp), 1819-1903; Holland, W. J. (William Jacob), 1848-1932; Huggins, William, Sir, 1824-1910; James, Arthur Curtiss, 1867-1941; James, D. Willis (Daniel Willis), 1832-1907; James, William, 1842-1910; Keeler, James Edward, 1857-1900; Knipping, Erwin, 1844-1922; Knobel, E. B. (Edward Ball), 1841-1930; Langley, S. P. (Samuel Pierpont), 1834-1906; Lincoln, Robert Todd, 1843-1926; Loomis, Eben Jenks, 1828-1912; Loud, F. H. (Frank Herbert), 1852-1927; Lowell, Percival, 1855-1916; Lyman, Albert Josiah, 1845-1915; Maxim, Hiram Percy, 1869-1936; Moore, Willis L. (Willis Luther), 1856-1927; Newcomb, Simon, 1835-1909; Norton, Charles Dyer, 1871-1922; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902; Palmer, George Herbert, 1842-1933; Parker, Gilbert, 1862-1932; Pickering, Edward C. (Edward Charles), 1846-1919; Pope, Albert A. (Albert Augustus), 1843-1909; Pritchett, Henry S. (Henry Smith), 1857-1939; Purrington, William Archer, 1852-1926; Robinson, Edward, 1858-1931; Rotch, Abbott Lawrence, 1861-1912; Safford, Truman Henry, 1836-1901; Saitō, Kuniji, 1913-; Schiff, Jacob H. (Jacob Henry), 1847-1920; Smith, Henry Preserved, 1847-1927; Stokes, Anson Phelps, 1838-1913; Swift, Lewis, 1820-1913; Taft, William H. (William Howard), 1857-1930; Thomson, Elihu, 1853-1937; Todd, David P. (David Peck), 1855-1939; Todd, Mabel Loomis, 1856-1932; Turner, H. H. (Herbert Hall), 1861-1930; Ward, Henry A. (Henry Augustus), 1834-1906; Whiting, Sarah Frances, 1847-; Wilder, Herbert Augustus, 1837-1922; Woolley, Mary Emma, 1863-1947; Wright, Arthur W. (Arthur Williams), 1836-1915; Young, Anne Sewell, 1871-; Young, Charles A. (Charles Augustus), 1834-1908; Aero Club of America; Allegheny Observatory; Alvan Clark & Sons; Amherst College; Blue Hill Meteorological Observatory; Japan Society (New York, N.Y.); Lick Observatory; Royal Greenwich Observatory; Yale University. Observatory; Yerkes Observatory
- Correspondence, PRE-1922 (1878-1922); Series I; 5 linear feet (13 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  This series is divided into two parts. The major section (ten boxes) is the general correspondence of David Peck Todd, arranged alphabetically by writer. A few drafts by David Peck Todd are included under the name of the recipient. Three boxes of family correspondence, which comprise the second part, are also arranged alphabetically by writer. Included here are letters from Mabel Loomis Todd to David Peck Todd from 1878 to 1922. His letters to her are in the Mabel Loomis Todd Papers. The letters from Millicent Todd Bingham to her father date from 1885 to 1922. Her letters to her parents jointly are also in the Mabel Loomis Todd Papers.
  The letters from Mabel Loomis Todd to her husband are important both for their number (nearly 400) and subject matter. They are very frank and often passionate in their expression of feeling, especially during the Todds' courtship years, and in the first years of their marriage. From the early 1890's until her stroke in 1913, she spent an increasing amount of time on lecture tours, and her letters offer interesting observations on the cities she visited and on the social life of the time. Her letters to David Todd after 1922 are in Series V, box 94, folders 86 and 87.
  Number in parentheses indicates number of items for that entry.
  - General Correspondence
    - A - Al (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Abbe, Cleveland
      General note
      See: box 9, Folder 324
    - Aero Club of America, (13), 1905-1906, 1908, 1913-1915, [ca. 1917], 1918-1919, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Aero Rapid Transit, Inc., (2), 1922 March 23, April 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Aeronautics; Ernest L. Jones (1), 1909 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Agassiz, A., (9), 1886, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Allegheny Observatory; S. P. Langley, (2), Circa 1880, 1912 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      See also: box 5, folder 176 See also: box 5, folder 185
    - Allen, Charles A., Navy Department, (5), 1898-1899, 1903, n.y. April (Box 1, Folder 7)
      See also: box 6, folder 218
    - Allen, Francis R., architect, (5), 1911-1912, 1914-1915 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Alvord, Emilie Louise, (3), 1878, [ca. 1878] (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Am - Ay (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - American Association for the Advancement of Science, (2), 1878, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - American Book Company, (19), 1899, 1901-1902, [1903], 1904, 1906, 1909, 1912, 1914-1916, 1920-1921 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - American Folk-Lore Society, (4), 1891, 1894 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - American Journal of Science, (8), 1888, 1890, [1911?], 1912, [1914?] (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Magazine, Ray Stannard Baker, (2), 1911, [ca. 1911] (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Amherst College Alumni Association, (15), 1893, 1897-1899, 1907-1908, 1910, 1913-1914, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Amherst Historical Society; B. W. Churchill, (3), 1900, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Anderson, Harriet, (3), 1911, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Andrews, Caro Lovejoy (Mrs. John), (10), 1888-1890, [1896] (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Anthony, Clara R. (including letters from Ruth Anthony and [Sarah Anthony]), (9), 1905-1907, [1910], 1911, [1914], n.y., undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Antrobus, R. L., (5), 1890-1991, 1895, 1900 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Anwers, Arthur, (1), 1880 February 19 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - D. Appleton and Company, (1), 1899 November 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Astor Library (New York Public Library), (5), 1877, 1882, 1885, 1888, 1906 (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Astrophysical Journal, (3), 1904-1905 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Authors' Clipping Bureau, (1), 1909 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Authors' Club of London, (2), 1909-1910 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Ba-Be (Box 1, Folder 28-29)
    - Babbott, Frank L., (5), 1893, 1898, 1911, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bailey, Alice Ward, (7), [1892], 1904, 1912, undated (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Baker, Robert H., Ladd Observatory, Brown University, (3), [1905], 1911 (Box 1, Folder 32)
      See also: box 80, folders 150-151 See also: box 115, folder 121
    - Ball, Sir Robert, (2), [1885?], 1907 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Barker, George F., University of Pennsylvania, (2), 1877 October 24, 1899 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Barnard, E. E., Lick Observatory, Yerkes Observatory, University of Chicago, (26), 1894, 1897-1999, 1910-1914, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Baxter, Arthur H., (5), 1908, 1909, 1916, n.y. December (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Bell, Alexander Graham, (3), 1922 March 4, 13, 25 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Bi - Bo (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Bischopsheim, R., Nice Observatory, (2), [1881], [1890] (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Billings, J. S., (3), 1895, 1902 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Bispham, Clarence Wyatt, (3), [1891], 1898 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Bispham, William, (10), 1897, 1900, 1903, [? January 23]
    - Blackburn, Henry, (3), 1885 November 14, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Boss, Lewis, Dudley Observatory (including reference to Astronomical Journal ), (3), 1879, 1909, undated (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Boston Athenaeum, (2), 1885 January 1, 1889 January 2 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Boston Authors' Club, (7), 1903-1904, [1908] Feb, n.y. Nov, n.y. March (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Boutet, Admiral H., (5), 1900, 1902, 1905 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Br - By (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Brashear, John A., astronomical instruments, (4), 1896, 1901, 1906, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
      See also: box 115, folder 121
    - Brazil, Observatorio Nacional do Rio de Janeiro, (1), 1913 January 18 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Brooklyn Standard Union; H. L. Bridgman, (11), 1897, 1904, 1906, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Brussels, Royal Observatory; A. Lancaster, (3), 1877, 1888, 1898 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Bryce, Lord James, (8), 1915, 1917-1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Bulkley, Barry, (7), 1898, [1907], 1910, 1914, 1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Bumham (?), S. W., (3), [ca. 1880], undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Byrd, Mary E., (3), 1905, 1911 (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - C - Ce (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Cable, George W., (3), 1895, 1915-1916 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Calderon, Y., Bolivian Legation, (3), 1907, [1911?] (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Campbell, Elizabeth B. (Mrs. W. W.), (1), 1918 April 27 (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Campbell, W. W., (1), 1907 November 11
      See also: box 5, folder 189
    - Canada: Department of the Interior, Office of Chief Astronomer; Otto Klotz, (2), 1904 December 12, 28 (Box 2, Folder 60)
    - Cannon, Dr. Annie J. (including clipping re: lecture by Dr. Cannon, 1925), (1), 1919 February 13 (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Cape of Good Hope, South Africa, Royal Observatory, (1), 1881 March 28 (Box 2, Folder 62)
      See also: box 4, folder 121
    - Carnegie, Andrew, (1), 1909 December 21 (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Charlois, A., Nice Observatory, (2), 1895 Apr, 1899 June (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Chentung Liang Cheng, Chinese Legation, (10), 1905-1907, 1909, 1911, n.y. July (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Chester, [W?], Rear Admiral, United States Naval Observatory, (4), 1903, 1905, undated (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Child, Edwin Burrage, (5), 1908, 1910, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Chittendon, Russell H., Sheffield Scientific School, Yale University, (2), 1908 January 7, 1911 April 11 (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Ch - Cl (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Clark, Alvan and Sons Corporation (including correspondence with W. L. Watts), (12), 1877, 1880, 1884, 1892-1893, 1898, 1905, 1906 (Box 2, Folder 70)
      See also: box 89, folder 25
    - Clark, John Bates, economist, (8), 1901, 1905, 1911, 1916-1918 (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Clark, William Bullock, geologist, (3), 1900, 1910, n.y. October (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Clarke, E. W., (5), 1911-1912 (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Co - Cu (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Coffin, C. A., (14), 1897-1900, 1907, 1914, 1916-1917, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 75)
    - Coffin (Professor) J. H. C., (1), 188[?] June 8 (Box 2, Folder 76)
      See also: box 105, folder 28
    - Columbia Alumni Association, (8), 1908-1909, 1913, 1915, 1922 (Box 2, Folder 77)
    - Commin, A., (6), 1900-1901, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
    - Compton, Charles W., (2), 1905 March (Box 2, Folder 79)
      See also: box 105, folder 30
    - Copeland, Ralph, Observatory, Dun Echt, Aberdeen, (5), 1877, 1880-1981 (Box 2, Folder 80)
    - Councilman, W. (including correspondence from Dr. George W. Crile), (4), 1907 March 22-May 2 (Box 2, Folder 81)
    - Craig, Thomas, (9), 1876-1880, undated (Box 2, Folder 82)
    - Cushing, J. P., Hillhouse High School, New Haven, (3), 1902, 1907 (Box 2, Folder 83)
    - Da - De (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Dakin, Arthur H., (16), 1903, [1905?], 1906, 1910-1915, 1919, n.y. May 5 (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Deering, James Charles, (3), 1917 Feb, Mar, May (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Derr, Louis, (14), 1921-1923 (Box 3, Folder 87)
      See also: box 4, folder 157
    - Deslandez, H., (4), 1899-1900 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Di - Do (Box 3, Folder 89)
    - Dickinson, Lavinia, (1), [1890] March 13 (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Dickinson, W. A., (1), 1889 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 91)